professor Dave here I'm gonna tell you
about elemental analysis
et's say we have an unknown
hydrocarbon
that's a molecule consisting of just
hydrogen and carbon
let's also say we want to know the
empirical formula of the hydrocarbon
or the lowest whole number ratio of
carbon to hydrogen atoms
in the molecule. is it 1 to 2, 1 to 3
3 to 5? a while back we figured out a clever way to decipher this ratio
when we combust hydrocarbons, that is
burn them in the presence of oxygen
we get carbon dioxide and water as
products
so all of the carbon in the hydrocarbon
ends up in carbon dioxide molecules
and all of the hydrogen ends up in water
molecules
we developed this nifty apparatus
whereby a sample of hydrocarbon with known
mass
is placed here over the flame. the tube
is open to allow oxygen to enter
and then the vaporized products travel
this way through these materials
one material absorbs water the other
absorbs
carbon dioxide. we weigh these materials
before and after the experiment
and the difference will be the mass of
water and carbon dioxide
absorbed respectively
so let's say we have a sample the benzene
but we have no idea what the ratio of
carbon to hydrogen is
we burn a 0.342 gram sample
and we collect 1.156 grams of CO2
in here. since CO2 weighs 44 atomic mass units
and a carbon atom weighs 12, each
molecule of CO2
is 27.3% carbon by mass
that means in the CO2 there are 0.316 grams
of carbon. so of the original sample
hydrocarbon
this much of it must have been carbon
and the remainder
must have been hydrogen
that makes the hydrocarbon 92.4% carbon
and 7.6% hydrogen by mass
we call that the percent composition of
benzene. let's go a step further and find
the empirical formula
if we pretend we have 100 grams of the
hydrocarbon
92.4 grams would be carbon and 7.6
grams would be hydrogen
using their atomic masses to convert to
moles we get roughly 7.6 moles
of each
which indicates a one to one ratio.
therefore
the empirical formula of benzene is CH. this
means that there's the same number of
carbon atoms
as hydrogen atoms in the molecule
if we want to find the molecular formula
which is the actual number of
atoms of each element in a molecule, we need
the molecular mass
let's say we know that for benzene the
molecular mass is 78
one unit of the empirical formula weighs
and 78 divided by 13 is six, this means
we need six units
the empirical formula to get the
molecular formula or C6H6
let's check comprehension
thanks for watching guys subscribe to my
channel for more tutorials
and as always feel free to email me